A Guide to the Virginia. Dept. of Education. School Division. Desegregation files, 1965-1971
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia. Dept. of Education. School Division. Desegregation files, 1965-1971
The Library of Virginia
29479
9 cu. ft. (18 boxes)
Virginia. Dept. of Education. School Division.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by the Division of Finance, Richmond, Va., 25 April 1977.
Scope and Content
Records, 1965-1971, including clippings, correspondence, forms, maps, and reports between Virginia public school boards and superintendents and the U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare, regarding efforts to desegregate Virginia schools. The records are housed in 18 boxes and arranged alphabetically by city or county name. The Library only has files for Fairfax-York Cities/Counties but nothing for cities/counties A-E.
After the 1954 Brown v. Board of Education Supreme Court decision which ruled "separate educational facilities are inherently unequal," state officials in Virginia continued to evade school desegregation and maintained a policy aimed at minimizing desegregation. State officials passed legislation making the school desegregation process more difficult through a policy known as Massive Resistance. It wasn't until 1959 when the federal courts overturned many of Virginia's antidesegregation laws that the process of desegregation began, although it proceeded very slowly and as late as 1965 few black students in Virginia went to desegregated schools.
At first Virginia adopted "Freedom of Choice" plans which did nothing to ensure school integration as it did not "ensure racial balance in schools." It wasn't until the U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare began to use portions of the 1964 Civil Rights Act to threaten localities with the loss of federal funding if they did not integrate their schools, that progress was made. Additionally a series of U.S. Supreme Court decisions increased the pace of school desegregation even more. In 1968 the Charles C. Green et. al. v. County School Board of New Kent County, Virginia, decision ended the "Freedome of Choice" plan and used other factors, such as the ratio of black to white students and faculty, to determine whether a desegregation plan was acceptable. Further Supreme Court decisions and pressure from the federal government helped to achieve the goal of school desegregation by the mid 1970s.
The desegregation files, 1965-1971, can be used to track the process of desegregation as city and county school boards had to show their progress through numerous forms and plans submitted to the U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare. Local school boards had to submit forms (Summary of enrollment and staff; and Estimated enrollment and staff) and desegregation plans to show their compliance with School Desegregation Plans Under Title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964. The forms contain the name of the school, county, total number of students, total number by race (White, American Indian, Black, Other), total number of Full time and part time teachers (also categorized by race) and Office staff. These numbers were used to show the ratio of black to white students and faculty to help determine if a school board had an acceptable ratio at each school. The plans included maps outlining school locations, changes to schools, and notices put in local newspapers showing the local adoption of school desegregation plans. The plans listed the steps being taken to desegregate the schools, such as changing a former white high school to now serve all high school students and to reassign faculty across the schools without any regard to race.
Included are school board resolutions and signed Assurances (or Statements) of Compliance with Policies for School Desegregation Plans, copies of court cases, notices sent to parents, and copies of hearings before the Commissioner of Education, Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare. Also included is correspondence from the U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare about the schools plans, stating whether or not the school boards have adequately met the purpose of the Civil Rights Act and whether they would receive federal funding or not.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by city/county.
Contents List
- Fairfax City, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Fauquier County [see also Oversize folder 1], 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Floyd County, [see also Oversize folder 1] 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Fluvanna County [see also Oversize folder 1], 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Franklin City, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Franklin City, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Franklin County [see also Oversize folder 1], 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Frederick County, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Fredericksburg [see also Oversize folder 1], 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Fries, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Galax, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Giles County, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Gloucester County [see also Oversize folder 1], 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Goochland County [see also Oversize folder 1], 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Grayson County, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Greene County [see also Oversize folder 1], 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Greensville County [see also Oversize folder 2], 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Halifax County, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Halifax County, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Halifax County, 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Hampton [see also Oversize folder 2], 1966-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Hanover County, 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Harrisonburg [see also Oversize folder 2], 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Henrico County [see also Oversize folder 2], 1965 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Henrico County, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Henrico County, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Henry County, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Henry County, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Henry County, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Highland County, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Hopewell, 1965-1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Isle of Wight County, 1965-1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- James City County, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- King George County, 1965-1970 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- King & Queen County, 1965-1969 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- King William County [see also Oversize folder 3], 1965-1969 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Lancaster County [see also Oversize folder 3], 1965-1970 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Lee County, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Lexington [see also Oversize folder 3], 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Loudoun County, 1965-1970 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Louisa County [see also Oversize folder 3], 1965-1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Lunenburg County [see also Oversize folder 3], 1965-1971 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Lynchburg, 1965-1971 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Madison County, 1965-1969 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Martinsville [see also Oversize folder 3], 1965-1971 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Mathews County [see also Oversize folder 4], 1965-1969 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Mecklenburg County [see also Oversize folder 4], 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Mecklenburg County, 1966-1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Middlesex County [see also Oversize folder 4], 1965-1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Montgomery County [see also Oversize folder 4], 1965-1969 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Nansemond County [see also Oversize folder 4], 1967-1971 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Nansemond County, 1965-1967 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Nelson County [see also Oversize folder 4], 1965-1970 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- New Kent County [see also Oversize folder 4], 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Newport News, 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Newport News, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Newport News, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Newport News, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Newport News, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Newport News, 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Norfolk [see also Oversize folder 5], 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Norfolk, 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Norfolk, 1968-1969 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Norfolk, 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Northampton County, 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Northampton County, 1967-1971 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Northumberland County [see also Oversize folder 5], 1965-1970 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Norton, 1965-1968 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Nottoway County [see also Oversize folder 5], 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Nottoway County, 1967-1968 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Orange County [see also Oversize folder 5], 1965-1970 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Page County [see also Oversize folder 6], 1965-1968 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Patrick County, 1965-1968 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Petersburg, 1965-1970 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Pittsylvania County, 1965-1967 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Pittsylvania County, 1967-1969 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Poquoson, 1965-1970 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Powhatan County, 1965-1968 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Prince Edward County, 1965-1970 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Prince George County, 1965-1970 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Prince William County, 1965-1969 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Pulaski [see also Oversize folder 6], 1965-1969 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Radford, 1965-1967 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Rappahannock County, 1965-1969 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Richmond City, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Richmond City, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Richmond City, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Richmond City, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Richmond City, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Richmond City, 1969-1970 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Richmond County [see also Oversize folder 6], 1965-1966 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Richmond County, 1967-1970 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Roanoke City, 1965-1970 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Roanoke County [see also Oversize folder 6], 1965-1969 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Rockbridge County [see also Oversize folder 6], 1965-1968 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Rockingham County, 1965-1970 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Russell County [see also Oversize folder 6], 1965-1970 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Saltville, 1965-1967 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Scott County, 1965-1967 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Shenandoah County [see also Oversize folder 7], 1965-1968 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Smyth County [see also Oversize folder 7], 1965-1968 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- South Boston, 1965-1971 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Southampton County, 1965-1966 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Southampton County, 1967-1969 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Spotsylvania County [see also Oversize folder 7], 1965-1971 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Stafford County, 1965-1968 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Staunton, 1965-1968 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Suffolk [see also Oversize folder 7], 1965-1968 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Suffolk, 1968-1970 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Suffolk, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Surry County, 1965-1970 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Sussex County, 1965-1969 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Tazewell County [see also Oversize folder 7], 1965-1968 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Virginia Beach, 1965-1968 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Virginia Beach, 1968-1970 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Warren County [see also Oversize folder 7], 1965-1967 (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Washington County [see also Oversize folder 7], 1965-1967 (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Waynesboro, 1965-1968 (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Westmoreland County [see also Oversize folder 8], 1965-1971 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- West Point, 1965-1969 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Williamsburg, 1965-1970 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Winchester, 1965-1969 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Wise County [see also Oversize folder 8], 1965-1968 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Wythe County [see also Oversize folder 8], 1965-1968 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- York County, 1965-1970 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Oversize, Fauquier-Greene Counties (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Oversize, Greensville-Henrico Counties (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Oversize, King William County-Martinsville (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Oversize, Mathews-New Kent Counties (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Oversize, Norfolk-Orange (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Oversize, Page-Russell Counties (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Oversize, Shenandoah-Washington Counties (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Oversize, Westmoreland-Wythe Counties (Box 18, Folder 8)